A Guide to the Tilghman H. Bunch Papers, 1799-1965
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Tilghman H. Bunch Papers 1799-1965
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6528-b
This collection consists of ca. 1300 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This material was a gift to the Library by Stuart E. Brown of Berryville, Virginia, on July 25, 1983.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 1300 items, 1799-1965, chiefly genealogical research materials on the Bunch, Crease, Lewis, Warwick, and related families, compiled by Tilghman Howard Bunch of Washington, D.C. There are also letters, and financial, legal, and business papers of these families, especially of the Lewis family of Bath County. Included also are personal papers of Bunch, including letters to his mother from Europe, Africa, and the Middle East during the 1920s, and letters to Bunch from family and friends.
Many of the letters were written during the late 1820s through the early 1840s by members of the Lewis family living in Missouri. These letters reveal much about life in Missouri, and include references to the rich land, good water, timber, and pasture; prices of corn, wheat, tobacco, cattle, and homes, business; state elections and the Democrats and Whigs; and illnesses. There is also mention of life in Alabama, Arkansas, Tennessee, and Chickasaw land. An 1831 letter from Charles Cameron Lewis, a student at the University of Virginia from 1825-1826, reveals that Negroes are very valuable property in and around Chickasaw land, and are treated better than those in southern Virginia. In an 1840 letter, Sophy Crease discusses Thomas Jefferson's campaign for judge in Arkansas, and Old Line and New Democrats.
Also of interest are two letters concerned with the surveying of property in Bath County. There is a June 1829 letter from John Brockenbrough, president of the Bank of Virginia in Richmond, to John Fry re Robert Mills; and, a letter from Robert Mills architect of the nineteenth century, perhaps best known for designing the Washington Monument. He was a protégé of Thomas Jefferson and was assistant to Benjamin Latrobe when the latter was Architect of National Buildings.
During 1924-1926, Tilghman Howard Bunch wrote letters to his mother, Laura Crease Lewis Bunch, while he was serving in the Navy. He often paints a vivid picture of his life in the Navy, sometimes describing maneuvers, torpedo and depth-charge practices, and various naval destroyers on which he served. These letters also contain descriptions and news of Beirut, Lebanon; Damascus, Syria; Monte Carlo, Monaco; Cannes, Nice, and Toulon, Frances; Leghorn, Naples, and Venice, Italy; the Riviera; the Acropolis and Athens, Crete, Lemnos, and Piraeus, Greece; Varna, Bulgaria; Constantinople, Turkey; Alexandria, Egypt; and Bizerte and Tunis, Tunisia. Bunch mentions having seen Henri de Jouvenal, French High Commissioner, in Syria.
There are letters to Bunch from distant relatives re Crease family genealogy, as well as other topics, Elizabeth Bohlinger writes about life in Little Rock, Arkansas; Little Rock Christ Church; and, General Douglas McArthur's visit there in July, 1952. Josephine and Lindley Crease refer to British Columbia's recovery from the depression with the reviving timber trade; and of world affairs. Marjorie Lloyd writes of life in England during and after World War II; Winston Churchill; Dwight Eisenhower; the Queen's and Prince Philip's visit to Malvern, Worcestershire; and politics in general.
There are also photographs of various members of the Bunch, Crease, Lewis, and Warwick families.
The genealogical research material compiled by Tilghman Howard Bunch include data on the following families: Anderson, Brooke, Bunch, Cochran, Cocke, Crawford, Crease, Fox, Francisco, Henderson, Hopkins, Howard, Hyde, Lewis, Newton, Smith, Tilghman, and Warwick.
Organization
The material in this collection is divided into the following series: I. Correspondence of the Bunch, Crease, Lewis, and Warwick families; II. Papers of the Bunch, Crease, Lewis, and Warwick families; III. Genealogical Papers; IV. Miscellaneous; V. Photographs; VI. Bound volumes; and VII. Oversize. Folders within each series are arranged chronologically, with the exception of the genealogical material which is arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Correspondence of the Bunch, Crease, Lewis and Warwick Families
  - Letters from Samuel Lewis to his Father 1823, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Letters from William Lewis to Samuel Lewis of Green Valley 1823-1830, 1842, 14 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Andrew Lewis to John Lewis and Samuel Lewis of Green Valley 1824-1832, 8 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Charles Cameron Lewis to Samuel Lewis of Green Valley 1826, 1830-1831, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Letters to Samuel Lewis of Green Valley re the Survey of Land in Bath County 1826-1830, 6 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from family and friends to SL 1827-1860, 1890, n.d., 9 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Samuel J. Bunch to John L. Bunch, Sr., his cousin 1832, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Letters from James M. Lewis and John Lewis to SL 1833, 1853, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Mary Myrtilla Bunch Campbell, Orlena Patsy Bunch Craighead, and friend to Elvira Cynthia Bunch Lathim 1835, 1853, 1856, 4 items (Box 1)
  - Letter from Samuel Bunch to John L. Bunch, Sr., his brother 1836, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Letters from Henry M. Lewis to SL 1838, 1842, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letter from Sophy [Ann Sophira] Crease to "Mr. Bertrand" re Thomas Johnson's campaign for Judge 1840, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Letters from John Lafayette Bunch to Elvira Cynthia Bunch Lathim and William Kenley Lathim 1844-1850, 4 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from C.C. Clay and Elvira Cynthia Bunch Lathim to John Lafayette Bunch 1850, 1856, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Elizabeth R. Lewis to SL 1850-1854, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Tilgham H. Bunch to William Kenley Lathim 1854, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Craven Peyton to Caroline Crease 1857, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letter from Adelaide F. Smith to W.K.L. 1859, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Letters from John W. Lewis and Family to Jasper Cope Lewis and Martha "Mattie" Cochran Warwick 1866-1879, n.d., 10 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Ann Crawford and Mary Miller "Millie" Crawford and Family to Martha "Mattie" Cochran Warwick 1866-1891, n.d., 12 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Benjamin Crawford to Jasper Cope Lewis 1870-1871, 9 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from J[ames] A. Cochran and James W. Crawford to Jasper Cope Lewis 1870-1871, 1884-1885, 1893, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from James Cochran, James McPherson Crawford, and George Randolph to Jasper Cope Lewis 1871, 1890, 3 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from relatives concerning deaths of Jane Newton Crease and John H. Crease 1872, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Benjamin Crawford to Jasper Cope Lewis 1872-1877, 9 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from B.M. Ellis to Jame sP. Van Lear 1875, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Letters from Laura "Lollie" Crease Lewis to John W. Lewis and Laura Crease Lewis 1882, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letters from Anthony Crease and Sarah Crease of Canada to [Laura Crease] Lewis and "Ann Sophie Crease?] 1888, 1904, 2 items (Box 1)
  - Letters to Jasper Cope Lewis re the title of land dispute for property located in Green Valley 1892-1899, 8 items (Box 1)
  - Letter from Virginia Clay Clapton to "My dear Cousin," one of the daughters of William and Elvira Lathim 1896, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Letters from Family and Friends to Harry L. Warwick 1898-1931, 9 items (Box 1)
  - Letters to Jasper Cope Lewis 1907, 1922, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Letters to J.C.L. re the land dispute with Graham 1916-1922, 16 items (Box 2)
  - Letters from Harry L. Warwick to William M. McCallister 1920, 2 items (Box 2)
  - Letters from Josephine Crease and Lindley Crease to Laura Crease Lewis Bunch and T.H.B., Jr. 1920-1947, n.d., 24 items (Box 2)
  - Letters from T.H.B., Jr. to his mother, L.C.L.B., and family 1924-1926, 54 items. 2 folders. (Box 2)
  - Letters from Elizabeth "Bessie" Peay Bohlinger and family to T.H.B., Jr. and Sue Peay Lewis 1935-1958, 82 items. 2 folders. (Box 2)
  - Letters from Marjorie Lloyd and family to T.H.B., Jr. 1940-1965, 14 items (Box 2)
- Papers of the Bunch, Crease, Lewis, and Warwick Families
  - Financial Papers
    - T.H.B., Sr.: Insurance Correspondence 1899, 1922-1924, n.d., 22 items (Box 3)
    - J.C.L.: Financial Papers 1920-1931, 14 items (Box 3)
    - Harry Lewis Warwick: Statements from the National Valley Bank of Staunton 1931-1939, 9 items (Box 3)
    - Jane Tate Van Lear Warwick: Financial Papers 1949, n.d., 3 items (Box 3)
    - H.L.W.: Statements from the National Valley Bank of Staunton 1952-1963, 10 items (Box 3)
    - H.L.W.: Financial Papers 1954-1967, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Sue Peay Lewis: Financial Papers 1957-1964, 24 items (Box 3)
  - Legal Papers
    - Deeds and Surveys of Green Valley and Bath County 1799(1871-1895) 1918, n.d., 16 items (Box 3)
    - Legal Correspondence and Papers of the Lewis Family 1818-1824, 4 items (Box 3)
    - Legal Papers of the Lewis Family 1864, 1868, 2 items (Box 3)
    - Last Will and Testament of J.C.L. (carbon TMs) 1920, 1 item (Box 3)
    - Last Will and Testament of Jane Tate Warwick (autograph and carbon TMs) 1927, 1946, 2 items (Box 3)
    - Deed between Harry L. Warwick and Relatives, Giving Property of "White Hill" to said Relatives 1954, 1 item (Box 3)
  - Business Papers
    - Business letters to John Lewis and Samuel Lewis of Bath County 1823-1831, 6 items (Box 4)
    - Business Papers of the Bunch Family 1834-1846, n.d., 7 items (Box 4)
    - Francisco, Frazier, and Lewis Families: Business Letters and Papers re Land Payments for Property Located in Green Valley 1854-1871, n.d., 16 items (Box 4)
    - Business Papers, chiefly Invoices, Promissory Notes, and Receipts, of SL 1858-1868, 26 items (Box 4)
    - Business Papers, chiefly Invoices, Promissory Notes, and Receipts, of J.C.L., Mattie Lewis, and Rachel Lewis 1866-1919, 18 items (Box 4)
    - T.H.B., Sr.: Business Correspondence 1907-1920, 7 items (Box 4)
    - T.H.B., Sr.: Mining Fields and Oil Lands 1907-1924, 20 items (Box 4)
    - T.H.B., Sr.: Eastern Selling Associated Claims 1918-1921, 14 items (Box 4)
- Genealogical Papers
  - Anderson Family 1935-1939, n.d., 15 items (Box 4)
  - Brooke, Crawford, Smith Families 1935-1950, n.d., 24 items (Box 4)
  - Bunch Family (folder 1 of 2) 1934-1949, n.d., 32 items (Box 4)
  - Bunch Family (folder 2 of 2) 1934-1949, n.d., 48 items (Box 5)
  - Bunch Family of Grainger County Tennessee 1926, n.d., 14 items (Box 5)
  - Bunch Family: Letters from Richard H. Bunch of Chicago, Illinois 1936-1962, 142 items. 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Bunch Family: Letters from Harry Carlock of Dadeville, Missouri 1938-1939, 12 items (Box 5)
  - Bunch Family: Letters from Mary Myrtella Lathim Cook Norris of La Mesa, California 1935-1938, 25 items (Box 5)
  - Bunch Family: Letters from the Society of Genealogists in London, England 1938-1942, n.d., 11 items (Box 5)
  - Bunch Family: Letters from Tennessee 1932-1952, 72 items (Box 6)
  - Bunch Family: Research Material 1941-1965, n.d., 86 items. 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Cochran, Francisco, Hopkins, Hyde, Lewis, Warwick Families 1918-1966, n.d., 21 items (Box 6)
  - Cocke Family 1935-1949, 1965, n.d., 22 items (Box 6)
  - Crease Family 1935-1946, n.d., 16 items (Box 7)
  - Crease Family: Christ Church of Little Rock, Arkansas 1934-1939, n.d., 11 items (Box 7)
  - Fox Family n.d., 1 item (Box 7)
  - Henderson Family 1935-1949, 1964, n.d., 11 items (Box 7)
  - Howard, Tilghman Families 1932-1946, 1961, n.d., 15 items (Box 7)
  - Lewis Family 1907-1947, n.d., 16 items (Box 7)
  - Lewis Family 1916, 1930-1958, 30 items (Box 7)
  - Lewis Family 1962-1967, n.d., 30 items (Box 7)
  - Newton Family 1935-1938, n.d., 11 items (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Bunch Family Bible Records n.d., 2 items (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous n.d., 3 items (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Tinttype of three unidentified men, probably of the Lewis Family; Tinttype of an unidentified Confederate Soldier, probably of the Lewis Family 1871, n.d., 2 items (Box 8)
  - Photograph of Lady Sarah Lindley Crease [1826-1922?] at Pentrelew, Victoria, British Columbia; Photographs of PentreLew and Saavich District 1921, 1938, 3 items (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, chiefly unidentified, connected with the Lewis Family 1931, n.d., 7 items (Box 8)
  - Photographs of Laura Lewis Bunch, Sue Peay Lewis, and Harry L. Warwick 1935, n.d., 4 items (Box 8)
  - Photographs of the [Bunch Family?] House in Rutledge, Tennessee ca. 1937, 4 items (Box 8)
  - Photographs of John F. Brooke [1838-1941] 1938, 1 item (Box 8)
  - Christ Church III, designed and built by W. Terry Field, Little Rock, Arkansas 1938, 1 item (Box 8)
  - Photograph of Richard H. Bunch [1865-1963?] 1945, 1 item (Box 8)
  - Photograph of Marjorie Lloyd, her husband, and a friend; Photographs of the Lloyd Home, State Vicarage, Kid-derminster, Worcestershire; Photographs of the Michael Lloyd Family 1945, 1962, 7 items (Box 8)
  - Photograph of James H. Shipp n.d. [ca. 1870], 1 item (Box 8)
  - Photographs of Elsie Bunch McKnight and Jennie Bunch Dill, daughters of John Lafayette Bunch and Ann Eliza Woolridge n.d., 2 items (Box 8)
  - Daguerreotype (photographic print) of John Bunch [1786-1837], brother of Colonel Samuel Bunch n.d., 1 item (Box 8)
  - Photograph of a portrait of Mary Stewart Bunch [1857-1924], daughter of John Thomas Bunch and Martha Isabella Hopkins n.d., 1 item (Box 8)
  - Photographs of Samuel Bunch's [?-1849] Tombstone, in Rutleedge, Tennessee n.d., 3 items (Box 8)
  - Photograph of a Monument to John Lewis in Gypsy Hill Park; Photographs of Fort Lewis n.d., 5 items (Box 8)
- Bound Volumes
  - Daybook for Green Valley Farm Sales 1916-1929, 1 item (Box 8)
  - Account Books of the Lewis and Warwick Families 1917-1919, 1929, 2 items (Box 8)
  - Journals re various activities kept by Harry L. Warwick 1932-1951, 3 items (Box 8)
  - Journal, kept by Sue Peay Lewis, of three trips to Florida w/ Harry L. Warwick 1938-1941, 1 item (Box 8)
  - Journal for "White Hill" Farm, Augusta County, kept by Harry L. Warwick 1948-1957, 1 item (Box 8)
- Oversize Items
  - Deed granting a tract of land in Bath County to James Givens 1799, Document (Box 8)
  - Deed granting a tract in Pocahontas County to Josiah Friel, signed by Virginia Governor Joseph Johnson 1852, Document (Box 8)
  - Mineral Map of the Arkansas Zinc and Lead District 1915, Printed (Box 8)
  - Map showing Property of the Boaz Oil Company n.d., Printed (Box 8)